<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Tim R Peterson Lab</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2021-05-11T10:57:07-05:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name></name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Conversation about Aging with Ira Pastor.</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/podcast/2021/01/11/Aging-Ira-Pastor.html"/>
   <updated>2021-01-11T03:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/podcast/2021/01/11/Aging-Ira-Pastor</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=x6HPXI_K2OQ&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=x6HPXI_K2OQ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/x6HPXI_K2OQ&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A conversation with Ira Pastor on his Progress, Potential, and Possibilities (PPP) Youtube program. We discussed our recent manuscript “Moonshots for Aging” that we recently published as well as other topics of the pharmaceutical industry.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Moonshots for aging.</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/manuscript/2020/11/03/Moonshots-For-Aging.html"/>
   <updated>2020-11-03T03:00:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/manuscript/2020/11/03/Moonshots-For-Aging</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7740370/pdf/nha-5-nha190064.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7740370/pdf/nha-5-nha190064.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kumar S, Peterson TR. Moonshots for aging. Nutr Healthy Aging. 2020 Nov 3;5(4):239-246. doi: 10.3233/NHA-190064. PMID: 33344796; PMCID: PMC7740370.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abstract. As the global population ages, there is increased interest in living longer and improving one’s quality of life in
later years. However, studying aging – the decline in body function – is expensive and time-consuming. And despite research
success to make model organisms live longer, there still aren’t really any feasible solutions for delaying aging in humans.
With space travel, scientists and engineers couldn’t know what it would take to get to the moon. They had to extrapolate
from theory and shorter-range tests. Perhaps with aging, we need a similar moonshot philosophy. And though “shot” might
imply medicine, perhaps we need to think beyond medical interventions. Like the moon once was, we seem a long way away
from provable therapies to increase human healthspan (the healthy period of one’s life) or lifespan (how long one lives).
This review therefore focuses on radical proposals. We hope it might stimulate discussion on what we might consider doing
significantly differently than ongoing aging research.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>ATRAID regulates the action of nitrogen-containing bisphosphonates on bone [Science Translational Medicine].</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/publication/2020/05/20/ATRAID.html"/>
   <updated>2020-05-20T09:30:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/publication/2020/05/20/ATRAID</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stm.sciencemag.org/content/12/544/eaav9166&quot;&gt;https://stm.sciencemag.org/content/12/544/eaav9166&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Links to access the article for free on Science Translational Medicine website:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://stm.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/abstract/12/544/eaav9166?ijkey=47pOgz4Wzinzo&amp;amp;keytype=ref&amp;amp;siteid=scitransmed&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://stm.sciencemag.org/cgi/rapidpdf/12/544/eaav9166?ijkey=47pOgz4Wzinzo&amp;amp;keytype=ref&amp;amp;siteid=scitransmed&quot;&gt;Reprint&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;http://stm.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/12/544/eaav9166?ijkey=47pOgz4Wzinzo&amp;amp;keytype=ref&amp;amp;siteid=scitransmed&quot;&gt;Full text&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lauren E. Surface, Damon T. Burrow, Jinmei Li, Jiwoong Park, Sandeep Kumar, Cheng Lyu, Niki Song, Zhou Yu, Abbhirami Rajagopal, Yangjin Bae, Brendan H. Lee, Steven Mumm, Charles C. Gu, Jonathan C. Baker, Mahshid Mohseni, Melissa Sum, Margaret Huskey, Shenghui Duan, Vinieth N. Bijanki, Roberto Civitelli, Michael J. Gardner, Chris M. McAndrew, William M. Ricci, Christina A. Gurnett, Kathryn Diemer, Fei Wan, Christina L. Costantino, Kristen M. Shannon, Noopur Raje, Thomas B. Dodson, Daniel A. Haber, Jan E. Carette, Malini Varadarajan, Thijn R. Brummelkamp, Kivanc Birsoy, David M. Sabatini, Gabe Haller and Timothy R. Peterson&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science Translational Medicine  20 May 2020:
Vol. 12, Issue 544, eaav9166
DOI: 10.1126/scitranslmed.aav9166; doi: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.aav9166&quot;&gt;10.1126/scitranslmed.aav9166&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nitrogen-containing bisphosphonates (N-BPs), such as alendronate, are the most widely prescribed medications for diseases involving bone, with nearly 200 million prescriptions written annually. Recently, widespread use of N-BPs has been challenged due to the risk of rare but traumatic side effects such as atypical femoral fracture (AFF) and osteonecrosis of the jaw (ONJ). N-BPs bind to and inhibit farnesyl diphosphate synthase, resulting in defects in protein prenylation. Yet, it remains poorly understood what other cellular factors might allow N-BPs to exert their pharmacological effects. Here, we performed genome-wide studies in cells and patients to identify the poorly characterized gene, ATRAID. Loss of ATRAID function results in selective resistance to N-BP–mediated loss of cell viability and the prevention of alendronate-mediated inhibition of prenylation. ATRAID is required for alendronate inhibition of osteoclast function, and ATRAID-deficient mice have impaired therapeutic responses to alendronate in both postmenopausal and senile (old age) osteoporosis models. Last, we performed exome sequencing on patients taking N-BPs that suffered ONJ or an AFF. ATRAID is one of three genes that contain rare nonsynonymous coding variants in patients with ONJ or an AFF that is also differentially expressed in poor outcome groups of patients treated with N-BPs. We functionally validated this patient variation in ATRAID as conferring cellular hypersensitivity to N-BPs. Our work adds key insight into the mechanistic action of N-BPs and the processes that might underlie differential responsiveness to N-BPs in people.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Drug target identification using CRISPRi/a screening.</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/funding/2020/04/22/CRISPRia-drug-target-ID.html"/>
   <updated>2020-04-22T02:30:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/funding/2020/04/22/CRISPRia-drug-target-ID</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Co-PIs: Tim Peterson, &lt;a href=&quot;https://gilbertlab.ucsf.edu/people/luke-gilbert-phd&quot;&gt;Luke Gilbert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our company, &lt;a href=&quot;http://bioio.tech&quot;&gt;Bio-I/O&lt;/a&gt;, was recently awarded a &lt;a href=&quot;https://sbir.nih.gov/funding&quot;&gt;phase I STTR grant&lt;/a&gt; from the NIGMS to use CRISPRi/a screening to identify drug targets for disease ranging from Alzheimer’s to Type II diabetes.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Sphingolipid Biosynthesis Inhibition As A Host Strategy Against Diverse Pathogens [Biorxiv].</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/manuscript/2020/04/10/Sphingolipid-CADs-pathogens.html"/>
   <updated>2020-04-10T02:30:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/manuscript/2020/04/10/Sphingolipid-CADs-pathogens</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.04.10.035683v1&quot;&gt;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.04.10.035683v1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sandeep Kumar, Jinmei Li, Jiwoong Park, Sydney K. Hart, Niki J. Song, Damon T. Burrow, Nicholas L. Bean, Nicholas C. Jacobs, Ariella Coler-Reilly, Anastasiia Onyshchenko Pendergrass, Tanya H. Pierre, India C. Bradley, Jan E. Carette, Malini Varadarajan, Thijn R. Brummelkamp, Roland Dolle, Tim R. Peterson&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;bioRxiv 035683; doi: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.04.10.035683&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.04.10.035683&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chloroquine is an anti-malarial and immunosuppressant drug that has cationic amphipathic chemical properties. We performed genome-wide screens in human cells with chloroquine and several other widely used cationic amphipathic drugs (CADs) including the anti-depressants, sertraline (Zoloft) and fluoxetine (Prozac), the analgesic nortriptyline (Pamelor), the anti-arrhythmic amiodarone (Cordarone), and the anti-hypertensive verapamil (Calan) to characterize their molecular similarities and differences. Despite CADs having different disease indications but consistent with them sharing key chemical properties, we found CADs to have remarkably similar phenotypic profiles compared with non-CADs we and others have previously screened. The most significant genetic interaction for all CADs was the initiating step in sphingolipid biosynthesis catalyzed by serine palmitoyltransferase (SPT). A comparison of genome-wide screens performed with diverse pathogens from viruses, bacteria, plants, and parasites including Ebola, adeno-associated virus AAV2, HIV, Rotavirus, Influenza A, Zika virus, Picornavirus, Exotoxin A, Cholera toxin, Type III secretion system and Shiga toxin, Ricin toxin, and Toxoplasma gondii showed SPT as a top common host factor and 80% overlap overall in top hits specifically with CADs. Potential sphingolipid-mediated mechanisms for the host response- and virulence-modulating effects of CADs involve autophagy and SERPINE1/PAI-1 (plasminogen activator inhibitor-1). Chloroquine has recently shown potential as an anti-viral agent for the novel coronavirus SARS-CoV-2, the causative agent of COVID-19 respiratory disease (19, 20). Our study demonstrates that numerous readily available drugs molecularly function highly similar to chloroquine, which suggests they might be considered for further pre-clinical investigation in the context of SARS-CoV-2. More generally, our work suggests the diverse pathogen mitigating potential of drugs that inhibit host sphingolipid biosynthesis such as CADs.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Novel type II diabetes and NASH drugs.</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/funding/2019/09/05/TypeII-diabetes-NASH-STTR-grant.html"/>
   <updated>2019-09-05T02:30:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/funding/2019/09/05/TypeII-diabetes-NASH-STTR-grant</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Co-PIs: Tim Peterson, &lt;a href=&quot;https://diabetesresearchcenter.dom.wustl.edu/brian-n-finck-ph-d/&quot;&gt;Brian Finck&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our company, &lt;a href=&quot;http://bioio.tech&quot;&gt;Bio-I/O&lt;/a&gt;, was recently awarded a &lt;a href=&quot;https://sbir.nih.gov/funding&quot;&gt;fast-track STTR grant&lt;/a&gt; from the NIDDK for Novel type II diabetes and non-alcohlic steatohepatitis (NASH) drugs we are developing.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Cell growth is an omniphenotype [Biorxiv].</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/manuscript/2018/12/05/Omniphenotype.html"/>
   <updated>2018-12-05T08:30:00-06:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/manuscript/2018/12/05/Omniphenotype</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2018/12/05/487157&quot;&gt;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2018/12/05/487157&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Jacobs, Ji Woong Park, Tim Peterson&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;bioRxiv 487157; doi: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1101/487157&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1101/487157&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genotype-phenotype relationships are at the heart of biology and medicine. Numerous advances in genotyping and phenotyping have accelerated the pace of disease gene and drug discovery. Though now that there are so many genes and drugs to study, it makes prioritizing them difficult. Also, disease model assays are getting more complex and this is reflected in the growing complexity of research papers and the cost of drug development. Herein we propose a way out of this arms race. We argue for synthetic interaction testing in mammalian cells using cell growth - changes in cell number that could be due to a number of factors - as a readout to judge the potential of a genetic or environmental variable of interest (e.g., a gene or drug). That is, if a gene or drug of interest is combined with a known perturbation and causes a strong cell growth phenotype relative to that caused by the known perturbation alone, this justifies proceeding with the gene/drug in more complex models like mouse models where the known perturbation is already validated. This recommendation is backed by the following: 1) Genes required for cell growth involve nearly all classifications of cellular and molecular processes; 2) Nearly all genes important in cancer - a disease defined by altered cell number - are also important in other complex diseases; 3) Patient condition and patient cell growth responses to many drugs are comparable. Taken together, these findings suggest cell growth could be broadly applicable phenotype for understanding gene and drug function. Measuring cell growth is robust, and requires little time and money. These are features that have long been capitalized on by pioneers using model organisms that we hope more mammalian biologists will recognize.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>ATRAID, a genetic factor that regulates the action of nitrogen-containing bisphosphonates on bone [Biorxiv].</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/manuscript/2018/06/04/ATRAID.html"/>
   <updated>2018-06-04T09:30:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/manuscript/2018/06/04/ATRAID</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2018/06/04/338350&quot;&gt;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2018/06/04/338350&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lauren Surface, JiWoong Park, Sandeep Kumar, Damon Burrow, Cheng Lyu, Jinmei Li, Niki Song, Zhou Yu, Abbhirami Rajagopal, Yangjin Bae, Brendan Lee, Steven Mumm, Gabe Haller, Charles Gu, Jonathan Baker, Mahshid Mohseni, Melissa Sum, Margaret Huskey, Shenghui Duan, Vinieth Bijanki, Roberto Civitelli, Michael Gardner, Chris McAndrew, William Ricci, Christina Gurnett, Kathryn Diemer, Jan Carette, Malini Varadarajan, Thijn Brummelkamp, Kivanc Birsoy, David Sabatini, Tim Peterson&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;bioRxiv 338350; doi: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1101/338350&quot;&gt;https://doi.org/10.1101/338350&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nitrogen-containing bisphosphonates (N-BPs), such as alendronate (Fosamax), are the mostly widely prescribed medications for diseases involving bone, with nearly 200 million prescriptions written annually. In the last few years, widespread use of N-BPs has been challenged due to the risk of rare but significant side effects such as atypical femoral fractures and osteonecrosis of the jaw. N-BPs bind to and inhibit farnesyl diphosphate synthase (FDPS), resulting in defects in protein prenylation. Yet it remains poorly understood what other cellular targets N-BPs might have. Herein, we perform genome-wide studies in cells and patients to identify the gene, ATRAID, that functions with FDPS in a novel pathway we name the TBONE (Target of Bisphosphonates) pathway. Loss of ATRAID function results in selective resistance to NBP-mediated loss of cell viability and the prevention of alendronate-mediated inhibition of prenylation. ATRAID is required for alendronate inhibition of osteoclast function, and ATRAID-deficient mice have impaired therapeutic responses to alendronate in a model of postmenopausal osteoporosis. Our work adds key insight into the mechanistic action of N-BPs and the processes that might underlie differential responsiveness to N-BPs in people.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Summer 2017 Updates</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/lab/updates/2017/08/23/Summer-2017-updates.html"/>
   <updated>2017-08-23T09:30:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/lab/updates/2017/08/23/Summer-2017-updates</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;new-people&quot;&gt;New people&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several new people joined the lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Sandeep Kumar comes to us from Kerry Kornfeld’s lab.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Harrison Rhee and Cheng Lyu are students at WashU.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This summer we also had India Bradley, who was an Amgen Scholar, with us from Howard University.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;funding&quot;&gt;Funding&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;New funding from Amazon Web Services (AWS) to support the MORPHEOME and PubMed natural language processing projects.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;New funding from the Nathan Shock Aging Center for the 10X Lifespan project. Ji Woong and Chris Chow wrote the AWS proposal, so congrats to them!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Bone basics</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/skeletal-system/2016/08/29/bone-basics.html"/>
   <updated>2016-08-29T09:30:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/skeletal-system/2016/08/29/bone-basics</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bone basics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-to-measure-bone-activity&quot;&gt;How to measure bone activity?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/bfr.png&quot; alt=&quot;BFR explained&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Osteoblasts:&lt;/strong&gt; Fluorescent microscopy of verterbrae to evaluate dynamic histomorphometry, in particular bone formation rate (BFR). Mice were injected with the fluorescent dyes, Calcein (in green), on day 0 and Alizarin Red (in red), 7 days later. The distance between the Calcein and Alizarin Red labelling provides a measure of bone formation rate and more specifically, osteoblast activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/trap.png&quot; alt=&quot;TRAP explained&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Osteoclasts:&lt;/strong&gt; Brightfield microscopy of vertebrae to evaluate osteoclast activity with Tartrate-Resistant Acid Phosphate (TRAP) assay Plastic sections of mouse L3-L4 vertebrae were used. The number of TRAP+ cells  (in red) on bone surface provides a measure of osteoclast activity.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Can mood be quantified?</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/mental-health/2016/06/29/diagnostic-for-mood.html"/>
   <updated>2016-06-29T09:30:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/mental-health/2016/06/29/diagnostic-for-mood</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Towards A Molecular Diagnostic for Mood&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can mood be quantified?&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Can humans live to be 1000 years old?</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/aging/2016/06/29/10x-lifespan-project.html"/>
   <updated>2016-06-29T09:30:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/aging/2016/06/29/10x-lifespan-project</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10X Lifespan Project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can humans live to be 1000 years old?&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Washington University School of Medicine St. Louis DBBS Faculty Poster Session</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/wusm/wustl/faculty/poster/session/2015/08/18/wusm-wustl-dbbs-faculty-poster-session.html"/>
   <updated>2015-08-18T09:30:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/wusm/wustl/faculty/poster/session/2015/08/18/wusm-wustl-dbbs-faculty-poster-session</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dbbs.wustl.edu/Resources/Pages/calendar_event.aspx?EvID=3728&quot;&gt;FULL INFO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seminar Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Date of Seminar: Tuesday, August 18
Start Time of Seminar: 2:30 PM
Sponsoring Department/Group: DBBS
Location: Eric P. Newman Education Center&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker(s) Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaker/Honorific: Faculty Members of the Division of Biology &amp;amp; Biomedical Sciences
Speaker’s Affiliation: Washington University in St. Louis
Title of Seminar: “DBBS Faculty Poster Session”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description:&lt;/strong&gt;
This poster session introduces students to the vast array of research being conducted by members of the Division of Biology &amp;amp; Biomedical Sciences. 65+ labs will be represented.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
